A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Art, Series C FA340
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Art, Series C
1931-1979
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Uht, Carol Kinzel
FA340
98.5 Cubic Feet
146 document boxes 13 oversized document boxes 40 bound volumes 20 record cartons
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller was born on July 8, 1908, in Bar Harbor, Maine, the third child of John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He graduated from the Lincoln School of Teachers College at Columbia University in New York City in 1926. Mr. Rockefeller attended Dartmouth College where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa, graduating cum laude in 1930 with an A.B. degree in economics.
After college, Mr. Rockefeller was active in family enterprises, including real estate, banking, and family philanthropies. His major business interests in time became focused on Rockefeller Center and Latin America. In 1938, he became the president of Rockefeller Center.
In 1935, because of his interest in national affairs and his desire to learn about U.S. business abroad, Mr. Rockefeller became a director of Creole Petroleum Company, the Venezuelan subsidiary of Standard Oil of New Jersey. This association led eventually to his deep, life-long interest in Latin America. He made extensive visits to Latin America in 1937 and 1939 to study economic, social, and political conditions. He resigned his directorship in the Creole Petroleum Company in 1940.
In 1940, Mr. Rockefeller and his four brothers organized the Rockefeller Brothers Fund to carry out a broad range of philanthropic activities.
Throughout his life Mr. Rockefeller was an avid supporter of the arts. He served as a trustee, treasurer, president, and chair of the board of the Museum of Modern Art, which was cofounded by his mother. In 1954, he founded the Museum of Primitive Art, which collected of indigenous art of the Americas, Africa, Oceania, and early Asia and Europe.
After his 1939 visit to Latin America, Mr. Rockefeller prepared a memorandum for President Franklin D. Roosevelt outlining his deep concern over Nazi influence and penetration into that part of the world. In the memo he recommended a U.S. program of cooperation with the nations of the western hemisphere to achieve better relations among these nations and to help raise their standards of living. Largely as a result of this memo, President Roosevelt asked Mr. Rockefeller in August of 1940 to initiate and head a new program ultimately known as the Office of Inter-American Affairs. Mr. Rockefeller served as Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, his first full-time position in public service.
Mr. Rockefeller served in this position until December 1944, when President Roosevelt appointed him Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic Affairs. In this post, Mr. Rockefeller initiated the Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace in Mexico City in February of 1945. It resulted in the Act of Chapultepec, which provided the framework for economic, social, and defense cooperation among the nations of the western hemisphere and set the principle that an attack on one of these nations would be regarded as an attack on all and jointly resisted.
Mr. Rockefeller signed the Act of Chapultepec on behalf of the United States. He also attended the United Nations Conference on International Organization in San Francisco in 1945. At the conference, there was considerable opposition to the idea of permitting, within the UN Charter, the formation of regional pacts such as the Act of Chapultepec. Mr. Rockefeller, who believed that the inclusion was essential, especially to U.S. policy in Latin America, successfully argued the need for regional pacts within the framework of the United Nations. The importance of this victory was underscored by the subsequent formation of NATO, SEATO, and the Rio Pact.
During these war-time years, Mr. Rockefeller also served as Chairman of the Inter-American Development Commission, which was established in June 1940 to reorganize and revitalize Latin American economies following the loss of European markets. He was also the U.S. Co-Chairman of the Mexican-American Development Commission to help Mexico emerge as an industrial nation in the transition from war to peace.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Assistant Secretary of State on August 24, 1945.
Upon his return to private life in New York in 1946, Mr. Rockefeller became chair of the board of Rockefeller Center and undertook a program of physical expansion. Two other initiatives during this period illustrate Mr. Rockefeller's continuing interest in Latin America and international economic development. In July of 1946, the Rockefeller brothers established a philanthropic organization, the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA). AIA financed nonprofit projects to ameliorate health, educational, agricultural, and other social problems in the poorer areas of Latin America. Nelson Rockefeller served as President from July 1946 to June 1953 and from January 1957 to December 1958. In 1947, he organized the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC), a business corporation to help raise living standards in foreign countries through new economic enterprises. In its early years, IBEC concentrated on enterprises in Latin America but later expanded its activities to other regions. Mr. Rockefeller served as IBEC President from January 1947 to June 1953 and from January 1956 to December 1958.
In his inaugural address in January 1949, President Harry S. Truman announced the Point IV program for providing technical assistance to developing nations. This concept was based in part on programs Mr. Rockefeller and his associates had developed through the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs and the private, philanthropic AIA. In November of 1950, President Truman asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the International Development Advisory Board. The Board was charged with recommending policies for carrying out the Point IV program. The Board's report, entitled "Partners in Progress," provided the basic blueprint for America's foreign assistance program.
On November 20, 1952, President-elect Dwight D. Eisenhower asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization, a group created to recommend ways to improve the efficiency of the executive branch of the government. As Chairman of that committee, Mr. Rockefeller recommended 13 reorganization plans to the President, 10 of which were approved by Congress. These plans achieved basic changes in the organization of the Department of Defense, the Department of Agriculture, and the Office of Defense Mobilization, among others. Another of the plans led to the establishment of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. In June 1953, Mr. Rockefeller was appointed Under Secretary of the new department. He was especially active in the department's legislative program, recommending measures that covered an additional ten million people under the Social Security program. He resigned as HEW Under Secretary in 1954 to become Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
While serving as Special Assistant, Mr. Rockefeller played a key role in the development of the "Open Skies" proposal for checking on world armaments through mutual air reconnaissance. He accompanied President Eisenhower to the Geneva Summit Conference in 1955, where the plan was proposed to the world by the President. Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Special Assistant on December 31, 1955.
Mr. Rockefeller first ran for public office in 1958 and was elected Governor of New York on November 4, defeating incumbent Averill Harriman. He took office January 1, 1959, and was subsequently re-elected Governor three more times, thus becoming the first Governor in the nation's history to be elected to four 4-year terms.
Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as a public servant in the federal government was a formative period in his life. By the time he left Washington to assume the governorship of New York, he had received a thorough education in the workings of the federal government. His chairmanship of PACGO permitted him to examine every aspect of the executive branch. This and his work in HEW exposed him to a wide variety of domestic issues. He gained experience in initiating legislation, in foreign policy and diplomacy, in domestic and international economics, and in national security and military affairs. In the process he also received an education in national politics and gained a reputation for being an effective and hardworking administrator. Most importantly, these appointments provided him with the opportunity to form the friendships and personal associations that served him throughout his political career.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Governor of New York in December 1973. In August 1974, President Gerald R. Ford nominated him to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon. Mr. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977. Nelson Rockefeller died on January 26, 1979, in New York City.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 04 C
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The Art series is divided in 6 subseries:
Subseries 1 - Works of Art, 1931-1946
Subseries 2 - NAR Artist Files, 1949-1979
Subseries 3 - CKU Reference Files, 1949-1979
Subseries 4 - Collection Inventories
Subseries 5 - Printed Material, 1935-1978
Subseries 6 - Canceled Art Files, 1949-1979
Scope and Contents note
The files in this series were created in the course of acquiring, managing, and disposing of pieces in Nelson A. Rockefeller's extensive art collection.
For the most part, these are the files of Carol Kinzel Uht, who served as Mr. Rockefeller's full-time curator from December 1949 until her death in 1978. Cynthia Bronson Altman joined the staff in 1971, serving as assistant curator and later as associate curator. Kendall P. Lutkins was responsible for the decorative arts portion of the art collection, including the Chinese pottery and porcelain. After Ms. Uht's death, Ms. Lutkins and Ms. Altman assumed most of these responsibilities and were also responsible for the eventual dissemination of Mr. Rockefeller's art collection in accordance with his will.
The documentation begins with some of Mr. Rockefeller's earliest purchases in 1931 and ends with his death in January 1979. A card file facilitates access to the various correspondence files and offers an abstract of the provenance, management, and disposition of each work of art.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller papers, Activities (FA338)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, AIA-IBEC (FA339)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Countries (FA341)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, DNA (FA342)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Family and Friends (FA343)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Oral Histories (FA344)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - New York City Office (FA345)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - George L. Hinman (FA346)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - Oscar M. Ruebhausen (FA347)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Projects (FA348)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential (FA349)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Washington, DC (FA350)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Ann C. Whitman - Politics (FA351)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Hugh Morrow Interviews (FA352)
Latin America; International relations -- United States; International relations; International economic relations; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Brazil; Arts; Business enterprises, Foreign; Business; Philanthropy -- New York (State); Civics; Civic improvement; Economic policy; Developing countries; Government policy; Philanthropy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Philanthropy -- United States; Federal government -- United States; Government agencies; Agriculture; Education -- Latin America; Art, Primitive; Agriculture -- Latin America; Political science; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Political campaigns -- United States; Social problems -- Latin America; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); State governments -- United States; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Public health -- Latin America; National security -- United States; New York (N.Y.); Economics; Education; New York (State); Venezuela; United States; Museum of Primitive Art (New York, N.Y.); Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
- Works of Art, 1931-1946; 1; 1 document box(es)
  Scope and Contents note
  This subseries documents the early years of Mr. Rockefeller's collection. It contains correspondence with art dealers regarding works of art offered for sale, correspondence regarding loans of works owned by Mr. Rockefeller to museums and galleries, and correspondence with artists.
  - NAR Paintings - Works of Art Offered and Declined, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Correspondence between NAR and artists, dealers, and other collectors offering paintings and works of art for sale. Most refused, few purchases. The folder contains a list of NAR Mexican collection in 1941.
  - NAR Paintings - Works of Art Offered and Declined, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence between NAR and artists, dealers, and other collectors offering paintings and works of art for sale. Most refused, few purchases.
  - Requests for Loans, 1939-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondence between NAR and galleries about loans of pieces of his collection to various shows and museums.
  - Bennett, Rainey, 1931-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Correspondence files. NAR financed a trip by the artist to Venezuela in 1945. Purchases several watercolors from the artist. Sent by NAR to Brazil and Argentina in 1941. Details planned exhibition of paintings.
  - Halpert, Edith, 1936-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondence files. As head of Downtown Gallery, asks for loans of pieces for exhibition; offers pictures for sale; some pieces purchased.
  - Yamanaka & Co., 1931-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Correspondence files. Chinese rugs and art purchases for an apartment. Other items offered, not purchases. Purchase of a ring for Mary Clark Rockefeller.
- NAR Artist Files, 1949-1979; 2; 17.6 Cubic Feet
  This subseries consists of an alphabetical file organized by artist name and a numeric file. Both document the acquisition, provenance, condition, cataloging, placement, and conservation of works of art. The alphabetical file primarily concerns pieces of modern art with documentation for each piece filed under the artist's name. The alphabetical file also contains correspondence with dealers, conservators, galleries, museums, and other institutions regarding the acquisition, care, and loan of works of art. The numeric file is an arrangement created by Mrs. Uht to categorize nonmodern art. Works of art were first designated by geographic region and then arranged by accession number. The index for this file is in Appendix A. Works of art documented within this series were in Mr. Rockefeller's collection at the time of his death in January 1979. Files pertaining to works of art that were no longer in the collection were transferred to the canceled art files (Subseries 6). The NAR art files were periodically sent to the Rockefeller family archives and were maintained there for several years. During that period some documents that do not belong in these files were placed in them.
  - A General (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Abe, Grey Echo Abeles, Sigmund Abrams, Ross Abularach, R. Adler, Lee African Arts Contemporary African Painting Albers, Josef Alexander Alex, G. Andrews, Oliver Arabshaki, Mass'oud
  - A General (Box 1, Folder 0001A)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material
    Allen, Patricia Dacca
  - Adams, Robert; Alpuy, Julio; Anuszkiewicz, Richard (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appel, Karel (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Archipenko, Alexander; Armitage, Kenneth (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arp, Jean (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Asawa, Ruth; Ashina, Takashi (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Asawa, Ruth; Ashina, Takashi (Box 1, Folder 0006A)
  - Ba General (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Baizerman, Saul Bakon, Yehuda Banerjee, Bimal Bardone, Guy Barlack, E. "Bases" Baskin, Leonard Bate, Stanley Battle of Fredricksburg Baumeister, Willi
  - Be General (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Beall, C.C. Bearden, Romare Beaudin Bela Belden, Monte Bell, Larry Bellesa Benazzi, Rafael Bender, Whitney C. Bennish, Grace Benoist, Ph. Ben-Shmuel, Ahron Benton, Fletcher Berge, Dorothy Berle Crawford, Alice Berrocal, Miguel Bertoia
  - Bi-Bu General (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Bianca (Sister) Biddle, Michael Bird, Junius (curator of Archeology at the American Museum of Natural History) Bimelin, Robert Blake, William Blanchard, S. Bloch, Georges Bluemer, Oscar Boiuna, Maria Bolivar, Simon Bonino (owner of The Galeria Bonino) Bonomi, Maria Bortner, Selmar Bossen, Jack Botero, Luisa Bouche Brandeis University Brandwen Brierre, Murat Bremmer, A.R. Briesen Briggs, Ernest Brown, Margaret Bryan Bryen, Burnel Budwick, S.G. Burkel, Fred Burrage, Mildred Bury, Pol
  - Bi-Bu General (Box 1, Folder 0009A)
    Bowns, Col. and Mrs. James
  - Balla, Giacomo (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Balla, Giacomo (Box 2, Folder 0010A)
  - Balla, Giacomo (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Balla, Giacomo (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bauermeister, Mary (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Baziotes, William (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Beauvoir, P.; Beckmann, Max; Bennett, Rainey; Bill, Max (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Blume, Peter (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Boccioni, Umberto (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Boccioni, Umberto (Box 2, Folder 0017A)
  - Boccioni, Umberto (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Boccioni, Umberto (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Boccioni, Umberto (Box 3, Folder 0019A)
  - Boccioni, Umberto (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Bodhisattva (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also Sect. 10-19
  - Bodhisattva (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Bodhisattva (Box 3, Folder 0022A)
  - Bodhisattva (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Bodhisattva (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Bonnard, Pierre (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Bontecou, Lee (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Bouts, Bernard (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Brady, Robert (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Brancusi, Constantin (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Brancusi, Constantin (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Brancusi, Constantin (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Braques, Georges (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Braques, Georges (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Braques, Georges (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Braques, Georges (Box 4, Folder 0034A)
  - Braques, Georges (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Braques, Georges (Box 4, Folder 0035A)
  - Brooks, James; Brown, Judith (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Brooks, James; Brown, Judith (Box 4, Folder 0036A)
  - Buchman, James; Bultman, Fritz; Burchfield, Charles (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Butler, Reg (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Ca-Cl General (Box 5, Folder 39)
    Cages Campbells, Richard Cancellations Candlesticks Carre, Louis Caruso, Bruno Cauldrons, (Copper) Cavaez Ceramic Animals Channel 17 WMHT Schenectady Channel 21 Chemicals Chillida, Eduardo Christi, Frank Chimeri, H. Christie's Chrysler Auction Clark, Mrs. Edmund Clay Bulls
  - Ca-Cl General (Box 5, Folder 0039A)
  - Col-Cor General (Box 5, Folder 40)
    Colin, Ralph Colker, Edward Colla, Ettorg Collins, Adele Colombian Heads Colton, Maurico III Columbus Citizens Committee Comtois, Ulysses Condition Photos Consuegra Conney, John D. Cooper, Warren Coreman's, Paul Correll, Alan Cortese
  - Cos-Cu General (Box 5, Folder 41)
    Cosmopolitan Club Constantini, Egidio Couper, William Crawford, Alice Berle Christiano, Renato Croft, Scott Crus-Saens, Gonzalo Cultural Affairs Currier, Nathaniel Creasey, John Will
  - Calder, Alexander (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Calder, Alexander (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Calder, Alexander (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Calder, Alexander (Box 5, Folder 0044A)
  - Callery, Mary (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Calo, Aldo; Campigli, Massimo; Capogrossi, Guiseppe (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Carlebach, Julius (Gallery); Castellanos, Julio; Cavalero, Christie; Century Exhibition (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Carlebach, Julius (Gallery); Castellanos, Julio; Cavalero, Christie; Century Exhibition (Box 6, Folder 0047A)
  - Cezanne, Paul (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Cezanne, Paul (Box 6, Folder 0048A)
  - Chadwick, Lynn (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Chadwick, Lynn (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Chadwick, Lynn (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Chagall, Marc (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Chagall, Marc (Box 6, Folder 0052A)
  - Chapin School (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Chapin School (Box 6, Folder 0053A)
  - Charlot, Jean (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Chinese Art (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Chinese Art (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Chinese Art (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Chinni, Peter (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Christensen, Dan; Ciarlo, Frances; Clark, Patrick; Cleveland Museum of Art; Cloar, Vista (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Cohen, George H.; Cortland, SUNY College; Coughlin, Marion; Craig, Martin (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - D General (Box 7, Folder 61)
    D'Amico, Mabel Da Silva Daub, Jean Hughs David, Charles Davidson, Jo Davie, Alan Davies, Arthur B. Day, Chon Dead Man Mask (African Mask) Dean, Abner Debany, Edythe B. de Lamonica Demuth, C. Dows, Olin Drinkard, Richard Drougas, Achilles Duccio Duchamp, Marcel Dufour, Bernard Dufy
  - Dartmouth College; Davies, Kenneth (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Day, Worden; Dechar, Peter; Degas, Edgar; Dehner, Dorothy (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Derain, Andre (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Derain, Andre (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - De Kooning, Willem (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Delvaux, Paul (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Dickenson, Sidney; DiSpirito, Henry (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Dorcely, Roland; Dubuffet, Jean (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - Duchamp-Villon, Raymond (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - Duchamp-Villon, Raymond (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Durchanek, Ludvik (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - E General (Box 8, Folder 73)
    Edion Egypt-Copt Egyptian Bowl Ekong Eliyakota Ely Emmerich, Andre (Gallery) Engel, Jules Engmart, Robert Epp, A.D. Ep'tycien Erobos-Morning (by John Day) Erni, Hans Ernst, Jimmy Everson, Anne W.
  - Early American; Effrat, Benni; Eielson, Jorge; Ekstrom, Arne (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Eliscu, Frank; Elkon, Robert (Gallery); Elmira, Arnot Museum (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - Eliscu, Frank; Elkon, Robert (Gallery); Elmira, Arnot Museum (Box 9, Folder 0075A)
  - Epstein, Jacob (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - Epstein, Jacob (Box 9, Folder 0076A)
  - Ernst, Max (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - Ernst, Max (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - Etrog, Sorel; Evans, Merlyn - Eskimo art (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - F General (Box 9, Folder 80)
    Fantin-Latour Feeley, Paul Feininger, Theodore Lux Fortune Magazine Fernandez, Louis Feron, Louis Filhos, Jean Fink, Herbert Fire Mansion Flavin, Dan Flor, Edward Formas, Leander Francis, Sam Frankenstein Frasconi, Antonio Frasier, D.H. Frazer Frost, A.B. Fulla, Ludovit
  - Feininger, Lyonel; Feine, Ernest (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - Fleischner, Richard (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Fleischner, Richard (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Fleischner, Richard (Box 9, Folder 0083A)